Register of the R. M. Hartwell collection
Hoover Institution Archives
R. M. Hartwell collection
1944-1990
91036
Hartwell, R. M. (Ronald Max), 1921-, collector.
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
5 manuscript boxes (2.1 linear feet)
Includes correspondence, minutes, conference papers, publications, and agenda of the Mont Pelerin Society, mainly in the form of photocopies, related to activities of the society in promoting laissez-faire economics and associated concepts of freedom. Includes questionnaires sent to Mont Pelerin Society members in 1984.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Friedrich A. von Hayek papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Mont Pèlerin Society records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1921 Born, Red Range, New South Wales, Australia
1950-1956 Chair of economic history, University of New South Wales
1954 Author, The Economic Development of Van Diemen's Land, 1820-1850
1956-1977 Reader in recent economic and social history and professorial fellow, Nuffield College, Oxford
1960-1968 Editor, Economic History Review
1961 Author, The Rising Standard of Living in England, 1800-1850
1971 Author, The Industrial Revolution and Economic Growth
1992-1994 President, Mont Pelerin Society
1995 Author, A History of the Mont Pelerin Society
2009 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Ronald Max Hartwell, author of A History of the Mont Pelerin Society, collected correspondence, minutes, conference papers, publications, and agenda of the Mont Pelerin Society, mainly in the form of photocopies, related to activities of the society in promoting laissez-faire economics and associated concepts of freedom.
In 1984, Hartwell sent questionnaires to members asking for basic information about their involvement with the society, opinions about the society, and anecdotes which might be of interest to historians. These questionnaires, along with related correspondence, can be found within the collection.
Mont Pèlerin Society.; Economic policy.; Laissez-faire.; Liberty.
- Mont Pelerin Society (Box 1-5)
  - Clippings in German, 1959-1984 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1964-1990 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1978 (Box 1-2)
    - 1956-1959 (Folder 1: 4)
    - 1960 (Folder 1: 5-6)
    - 1961-1963 (Folder 1: 7-9)
    - 1964-1967 (Folder 2: 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1970-1973 (Folder 2: 3)
    - 1974-1976 (Folder 2: 4)
    - 1977-1978 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Finances file, 1949-1988 (Box 2)
    - Annual reports of the treasurer, 1949-1988 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1980 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Meetings file, 1944-1985 (Box 2-4)
    - General, 1964-1969 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Mont Pèlerin, Switzerland, 1947 (Box 3)
      - General, 1944, 1947 (Folder 3: 1-2)
      - Albert Hunold's notes on the first meeting, 1947 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Seelisberg, Switzerland, 1949 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Bloemendaal, Holland, 1950 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Beauvallon, France, 1951 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Seelisberg, Switzerland, 1953 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Venice, Italy, 1954 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Berlin, Germany, 1956 (Folder 3: 9)
    - St. Moritz, Switzerland, 1957 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Princeton, United States, 1958 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Oxford, England, 1959 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Kassel, Germany, 1960 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Turin, Italy, 1961 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Munich, Germany, 1970 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Rockford, United States, 1971 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Montreux, Switzerland, 1972 (Folder 3: 17)
    - Guatemala City, Guatemala, 1973 (Folder 3: 18)
    - Brussels, Belgium, 1974 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Hillsdale, United States, 1975 (Folder 3: 20)
    - St. Andrews, Scotland, 1976 (Folder 3: 21)
    - Paris, France, 1976 (Folder 3: 22)
    - Amsterdam, Holland, 1977 (Folder 3: 23)
    - Hong Kong, 1978 (Folder 3: 24)
    - Stanford, United States, 1980 (Folder 4: 1-2)
    - Vina del Mar, Chile, 1981 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Stockholm, Sweden, 1981 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Berlin, Germany, 1982 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Vancouver, Canada, 1983 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Cambridge, England, 1984 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Paris, France, 1984 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Sydney, Australia, 1985 (Folder 4: 9-10)
  - Membership directories, 1983, 1987, 1989 (Folder 4: 11)
  - The Mont Pèlerin Quarterly, 1960-1962 (Folder 4: 12)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes "How the Mont Pèlerin Society Lost Its Soul"
  - Presidents' reports, 1947-1958 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Printed matter, 1974 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Questionnaires, 1984 (Folder 5: 1-3)
    Includes questionnaires from Manuel Ayau, Peter Thomas Bauer, Martin Bronfenbrenner, James M. Buchanan, Andrzej Brzeski, Jameson G. Campaigne, John Chamberlin, Harold Demsetz, Donald J. Devine, Christian Gandil, Herbert Giersch, Ernest van den Haag, Ralph Harris, David R. Henderson, Jack Hirshleifer, Arthur Kemp, Denison Kitchel, George Koether, Ulrich Leffson, K. T. Li, Alberto Benegas Lynch, Paul W. McCracken, Tibor R.Machan, Antonio Martino, John H. Moore, Dallin H. Oaks, Noel B. Reynolds, Rita Ricardo-Campbell, George C. Roche III, Thomas Anderson Roe, Richard N. Rosett, George Stigler, Arthur Shenfield, Vernon L. Smith, Beryl W. Sprinkel, John M. Templeton, Stephen J. Tonsor, G. Carl Wiegand, Walter Edward Williams, Hans Willgerodt, Ricardo Zinn, and others. Includes related correspondence.
  - Speeches and writings
    - "Europe's Historical Contribution to Western Civilization,", undated (Folder 5: 4)
    - "The Re-emergence of Liberalism? The Role of the Mont Pelerin Society" or "Concerned Liberals: The Founding of the Mont Pelerin Society,", undated (Folder 5: 5)